i want to talk to you about graphql this
is because we just finished recording
subtitling and uploading a free two and
a half hour graphql course that you can
take right now for free but before you
click on the link below watch this video
until the end because we are going to
talk about graphql where does it come
from why was it created what problems
does it fix and most importantly of all
who should learn graphql a graphql was
created by facebook and it has been
powering the facebook apps since 2012.
now in 2015 facebook open sourced the
graphql specification specification or
spec means that graphql is just a set of
rules and ideas written on a paper that
is the paper that was open sourced
graphql is just an idea and for this
reason you cannot actually go to a
website and click download graphql what
we can actually download and use are
graphql implementations implementations
are created by really cool people that
sit and read the graphql specification
and translate those rules to actual code
this means that graphql is not actually
bounded to any specific language you can
use graphql in javascript python rost c
sharp java whatever you want as long as
somebody implemented the graphql spec
now to understand why graphql was
created we have to understand what
problem does it fix so now let's talk
about what is the point of graphql
graphql was created by facebook to fix
some problems that they were having with
rest apis so for this we have to
remember what apis are an api is an
interface that we can use in this
context to communicate with a server in
your iphone or android you have the
instagram app this instagram app has to
communicate with the facebook's servers
this communication happens using an api
now the most popular kind of api is a
rest api and rest apis are very easy to
understand the way rest apis work is by
having multiple urls every url is
different and unique and they all give
you a different kind of data let's take
the twitter rest api for example if you
use the twitter app or the website when
you go to the profile of elon musk for
example your app or your browser are
both going to send a request to this url
this is a url that will give you all the
tweets for a user provided the id that
id in this case is the id of elon musk
on twitter's database this url will not
return a website we are usually used to
urls returning a website when you go to
youtube.com you are used to seeing a
website for this kind of url which is a
rest api url will not give you a website
it will give you just data it will give
you data in a json format now this data
is what your iphone or your browser are
going to take and then they are going to
paint it in a beautiful way and the
twitter rest api is full of this kind of
urls if for example we want to know who
is elon musk following we will have to
visit a url like this one or if you want
to know who is following elon musk all
we have to do is go to a url like this
one
these urls are actually not visited by
humans this is the url that your phone
would request to get that data and like
i said the rest api of twitter is full
of urls like this that are very useful
for every different case for example if
we search for the word banana on the
twitter app for ios and android the
twitter app is going to send a request
to the twitter api to a url like this
one searching for banana
this way of structuring an api by
creating a different url for everything
is called rest and rest apis are really
really popular but rest has two big
problems that facebook ran into and they
are called over fetching and under
fetching to fix these two problems is
why facebook created graphql so let's
start with over fetching overfetching
means that you receive more data than
what you actually need so for example
using the excellent the movie database
rest api which is a database that you
can use to get almost any info you want
on movies or tv shows if we want to know
which movies are coming up soon all we
have to do is go to the slash movie
slash upcoming url now when we receive
that response we're gonna receive
something like this
as you can see here we get data about
the movie the title the popularity the
release date among many other things now
please imagine that we were making a
movie app and we received this data but
what we actually show to the user is
just the title of the movie if we do
this if we only show the title of the
movie and nothing else we are basically
wasting all the data that we just
received it doesn't make sense to fetch
all the data if we are not going to use
it and that is over fetching instead if
we were able to only ask for the data
that we actually are going to need the
database wouldn't work so hard and the
data that has to travel between the
server and the phone for example
wouldn't be so big making the loading
time less graphql fixes this graphql is
a query language that is the ql in
graphql graphql allows you to
specifically ask for the server for
exactly what you need if the movie
database was using graphql instead of
rest rather than sending a request to
this url and getting all this data and
then wasting the data we would instead
send a query using graphql to the server
and the query would look something like
this with this query we would receive
data in this shape as you can see with
graphql we don't need to receive the
data that we don't want and we are able
to ask for the data that we exactly want
nothing more and nothing less now let's
talk about under fetching which is the
opposite of over fetching under fetching
means that you fetch less data than what
you actually need if we're making a
movie app and we want to show two lists
of movies one for the movies that are
coming up soon and one for the movies
that are playing right now if we were
using a rest api we would have to make
two requests to two separate urls in the
case of the movie database rest api we
would have to make a request to slash
movie slash upcoming in slash movie
slash now playing this means that our
phone ios or android or our website is
going to have to make two requests it
will have to hit two urls one after the
other that might increase loading time
if we were using graphql because we can
ask for exactly what we want we don't
have to send two requests instead in one
query we can ask for the movie that are
playing right now and the movies that
are gonna play soon and with a query
like this one we will receive a response
like this one how cool is this we don't
have to fetch two urls we also don't do
over fetching because we don't get extra
data that we don't need this is how
graphql solves under fetching and
overfetching in a super elegant way but
this is not all graphql can do graphql
has other features that make building
apis with graphql a very pleasant
experience but unfortunately we don't
have time for all the graphql features
on this video this is why i made a two
and a half three hour graphql course
that you can take right now click on the
link below and there you will see what
makes graphql even more awesome than
what we already saw and how you can make
your own graphql api now the question is
who should learn graphql and the answer
is everybody if you have built a server
before if you have made a red api before
i beg you try graphql and i'm sure
you're going to like it it's a very
different way of building apis what i am
sure you are going to enjoy thank you
for watching this video let me know in
the comments if you have used graphql if
you want to use graphql in the future
what do you think about it i'm going to
be looking at them right now thank you
so much for watching stay happy stay
free at kimchi come zamida san angelo
see you on the next one bye